Guide to the Charles L. Bernheimer Papers 1877-1935 (bulk 1906-1920) MS 58
New-York Historical Society
Charles L. Bernheimer papers
1877-1935 (bulk 1906-1920)
New-York Historical Society
Bernheimer, Charles L. (Charles Leopold), 1864-1944
MS 58
7 Linear feet in 7 record cartons and 1 over-sized folder
Correspondence, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and photographs belonging to Charles L. Bernheimer (1864-1944). Bernheimer was a businessman and explorer that participated in several civic service related activities in New York City. The collection contains drafts and correspondence regarding Bernheimer's peace proposals for the termination of World War I. There is correspondence and other documents related to Bernheimer's work as a strike arbitrator. The collection also contains records of several political organizations that supported fusion politics and reform in New York's municipal government in the early twentieth century.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
The collection is organized by topic with much of the original ordering, such as content of the folders, remaining intact as found by the processing archivist in June 2019.
Biographical / Historical
Charles L. Bernheimer (1864-1944) was a Jewish merchant, arbitrator, and businessman who was involved in several civic activities in New York City. He was born in Ulm, Germany in 1864 and immigrated to the United States in 1880. Upon his arrival, he worked at the firm of Adolph Bernheimer for wholesale dry foods, which later became the Bear Mill Manufacturing Company of which he was president from 1907 to 1929. As a merchant, he was chairman of both the Trade Relations Council and the Council of Textile Executives.
In addition to his work in business, Bernheimer was involved in the political scene in New York. He was the treasurer of the Citizens' Municipal Campaign, also known as the "Committee of 107," which helped elect John Purroy Mitchel as mayor of New York City. The Citizens' Municipal Campaign was an anti-Tammany effort that sought to elect non-partisan politicians that would support progressive reform. Bernheimer was also an arbitrator for labor disputes as he was Chairman of the Committee on Arbitration of the New York Chamber of Commerce. He helped settle numerous strikes regarding the garment industry.
Charles Bernheimer was also an explorer and took several trips to the Southwest where he discovered dinosaur tracks and Native American artifacts. Furthermore, he was a congregant of Temple Emanu-El, the first reform Jewish congregation in New York City.
Throughout 1914 and 1915, Bernheimer drafted his proposed settlement to end World War I; he saw the United States as being in a unique position to act as an international arbitrator that would oversee a peace resolution and ensure its continuation.
He married Clara Silberman in 1893 and had two daughters, Mrs. Hellen B. Halle and Mrs. Alice B. Pallain.
After numerous years of civic service, Bernheimer died in 1944 at age seventy-nine.
[This biographical note is drawn from the New York Herald Tribune obituary of Charles L. Bernheimer (see box 6, folder 25).]
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Charles L. Bernheimer in 1943.
Scope and Contents
The Charles L. Bernheimer papers contain correspondence and records related to several activities that Bernheimer was involved with.
There are drafts and revisions of Bernheimer's "A Businessman's Plan for Settling the War" which was his own peace proposal for the termination of World War I. The collection contains correspondence regarding the proposal as Bernheimer sent it to numerous friends and public figures, including President Woodrow Wilson. In addition, there are clippings from newspapers and personal records related to the proposals and World War I in general.
The collection also includes documents and correspondence from Bernheimer's time working as an arbitrator in labor disputes with the Committee on Arbitration of New York Chamber of Commerce. There are records of strike settlements from many garment industries such as the Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Industry, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the American Clothing Manufacturer's Association.
In addition, there is correspondence associated with the Safety First movement which was an organization that focused on several aspects of public safety such as street traffic and signaling devices on automobiles.
There are also documents, official records, and correspondence regarding numerous political organizations that Bernheimer was involved with such as the Citizens' Municipal Committee and the Fusion committee as well as local and national political campaigns.
Documents related to other topics are also present including a daylight savings time proposal, parks maintenance plans, subway system construction ideas, unemployment projects, and revisions for New York's bank laws.
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Banking law -- New York (State); Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Circulars; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Daylight saving; Garment Workers' Strike, New York, N.Y., 1912-1913.; Industrial relations -- New York (State); Labor unions -- Political activity; Mayors -- New York (State) -- New York; Memorandums; Minutes; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 1898-1951; North America -- Discovery and exploration; Political campaigns -- New York (State) -- New York; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1912; Scrapbooks.; Speeches; Strikes and lockouts -- Clothing trade -- New York (State); World War, 1914-1918 -- Peace; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Adler and Ast (Firm); Citizens' Municipal Committee (New York, N.Y.); Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers' Protective Association (New York, N.Y.); Mitchel, John Purroy, 1879-1918; National Trades Relations Council; New York Chamber of Commerce. Committee on Arbitration; Parks Rehabilitation Committee (New York, N.Y.); Safety First Federation; Safety First Society (New York, N.Y.); Textile Integrity Guild (New York, N.Y.)
- Peace proposals, drafts, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Peace proposals, correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes correspondence to friends and public figures regarding Bernheimer's peace proposal.
- Peace proposals, correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes letters addressed to President Woodrow Wilson.
- Peace proposals, correspondence (2 folders), 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Peace proposals, correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Letters addressed to Vice President Thomas Marshall.
- Peace proposals, correspondence (3 folders), 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
- Peace proposals, correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes letters addressed to Andrew Carnegie and William H. Taft.
- Peace proposals, business records, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes personal records relating to Bernheimer's publicity efforts for his peace proposal.
- Peace proposals, correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence with General Howard Otis.
- Peace proposals, translations, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Translations of Bernheimer's peace proposal in French, Italian, Spanish, and Dutch.
- Peace proposals, clippings, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Newspapers, 1915-1920 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Documents from Bernheimer's trip to Europe during the beginning of World War I. Includes documents in German, Swiss, and French.
- Labor strikes, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Includes records and correspondence regarding the Men's Clothing Strike and the Committee on Arbitration of the New York Chamber of Commerce.
- Labor strikes (3 folders), 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  Includes correspondence and records of strikes related to the Cloak, Suit and Skirt Industry.
- Labor strikes, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Includes correspondence and records of strikes related to the Adler and Ast controversy.
- Labor strikes (2 of 3 folders), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  Includes correspondence and records of strikes related to the Cloak, Suit and Skirt Industry, Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America and the American Clothing Manufacturer's Association.
- Labor strikes (1 of 3 folders). Oversize, 1916-1918 (Folder Oversize-Medium)
  Poster from the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America declaring the beginning of a general strike for the garment industry on January 13, 1916. The poster is written in English, Hebrew, and Italian.
- Labor strikes (5 folders), 1915-1918 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  Includes correspondence, publications, and records from strikes regarding the garment industry.
- Labor strikes (4 folders), 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 6-9)
  Includes records of conciliation efforts from strikes regarding the Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturer's Industry. Letter addressed to Samuel Gompers.
- Labor strikes (2 folders), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  Includes petition to President Woodrow Wilson regarding the garment worker's strike in New York City.
- Safety First, correspondence (5 folders), 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
  Includes correspondence associated with public safety efforts.
- Safety First, correspondence, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Safety First, correspondence, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Correspondence with Andrew Carnegie's secretary, J.A. Poynton, as well as references to conversations with John D. Rockefeller's secretary, Jerome D. Greene.
- Safety First, correspondence (3 folders), 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  Includes records regarding street traffic safety and signalling devices for automobiles.
- Safety First, by-laws and contracts, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Safety First, conferences and forum, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes records from events organized by Safety First.
- Safety First, promotional letters (2 folders), 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- Citizens' Municipal Committee, financial records, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Records of contributions to the Citizens' Municipal Committee including those of John D. Rockefeller.
- Citizens' Municipal Committee (5 folders), 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 11-15)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, and records relating to the role of the Citizens' Municipal Committee of 107 in the election of Mayor John Purroy Mitchel; the financial contributions to the Citizens' Municipal Committee, including those of John D. Rockefeller; the disbanding of the Citizens' Municipal Committee; and the appointment of several individuals to certain political positions.
- Citizens' Municipal Committee, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Includes records of those who contributed to the Citizens' Municipal Committee.
- Fusion Campaign, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Includes correspondence and records related to the Fusion mayoralty campaign of 1913.
- Citizen's Municipal Committee, early papers (3 folders), 1913 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  Includes correspondence related to the creation of the Citizens' Municipal Committee.
- Citizens' Municipal Committee, 1916-1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Includes records related to municipal politics and New York City's efforts to Americanize immigrants.
- Citizens' Municipal Committee (9 folders), 1913 (Box 4, Folder 2-9)
  Includes correspondence and records related to the financial contributions for the Citizens' Municipal Committee.
- Miscellaneous (2 folders), 1913 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  Includes correspondence, records, and ephemera associated with the Citizens' Municipal Committee.
- New Municipal Campaign Committee, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Includes correspondence regarding Mayor John Purroy Mitchell and his re-election campaign.
- Fusion Committee of 1917 (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 13-17)
  Records of the Fusion Committee's effort to re-elect Mayor John Purroy Mitchel including correspondence with potential contributors to the campaign; lists of financial contributions; pamphlets regarding the Fusion Committee's purpose; and documents about the 1917 election.
- Political pamphlets, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Includes political campaign pamphlets and other publications for the 1917 re-election of Mayor John Purroy Mitchel.
- Fusion Campaign, clippings, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Includes clipping from "The Fusion Flashlight."
- Political campaigns, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Includes pamphlets from the William M. Bennett Campaign Committee as well as other political documents regarding the 1917 municipal election.
- Political campaigns, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Includes correspondence regarding several municipal campaigns from both Republican and Fusion candidates during the 1917 election.
- Political campaigns, 1912 (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  Includes correspondence and contribution records regarding the 1912 Congressional Campaign in the 18th Congressional District for S. Walter Kaufman. Records of the Republican Party's 1912 campaign.
- Miscellaneous, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  Includes personal notes, correspondence, and clippings. Some items relate to the 1913 municipal campaign.
- Political contributions (3 folders), 1913 (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  Includes records of financial contributions to the Fusion Campaign and the Citizens' Municipal Campaign.
- Citizens' Municipal Committee (2 folders), 1913 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  Correspondence regarding the financial contributions to the Citizens' Municipal Committee.
- Daylight Savings Time Committee, 1916-1918 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Includes correspondence and pamphlets reagrding the movement to pass federal legislation for a Daylight Savings Time bill.
- Mayor's Committee on Unemployment (2 folders), 1914-1916 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
  Includes correspondence, pamphlets, reports, and proposals related to unemployment efforts in New York City.
- Miscellaneous, 1913-1919 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Personal correspondence regarding bank law revisions and Mayor John Purroy Mitchel's funeral.
- Newspapers, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Clippings related to strike activity.
- Newspapers, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  New York Journal of Commmerce
- New York Bank Law revision, 1913-1914 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  Includes records, pamphlets, and correspondence regarding the efforts to pass bank law revisions in New York state.
- Red Cross, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Correspondence related to Charles Bernheimer's work with the Red Cross.
- Speech materials, 1914-1918 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  Clippings and personal notes.
- Trade Relations Council, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  Includes minutes, clippings, and personal notes regarding the Trade Relations Council.
- New York Bank Law Revisions (2 folders), 1913-1914 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  Includes clippings, pamphlets, personal notes, and correspondence related to the New York bank law revision proposals.
- Speech materials, 1910-1918 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Includes pamphlets, correspondence, and personal notes regarding World War I peace talks and the 1912 presidential election.
- Fifth Avenue Association, 1917- 1921 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, and publications regarding the Fifth Avenue Assciation's efforts to restrict building heights.
- Chamber of Commerce, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Includes personal writings related to the Chamber of Commerce.
- Safety Deposit Boxes, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Includes records of contents from Charles Bernheimer's safety deposit box.
- Economic opinions, 1920-1931 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Includes personal correspondence related to Charles Bernheimer's work on the Chamber of Commerce as well as publications about the Great Depression.
- New York Federation of Churches, 1914-1915 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence and publications related to the New York Federation of Churches' work to combat unemployment as well as documents regarding the Committee for Immigrants in America.
- Honest Ballot Association, 1918-1922 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Includes correspondence and publications related to the work of the Honest Ballot Association in ensuring the enfranchisement of all who are eligible.
- Textile Integrity Guild, 1930-1935 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, and records detailing the works of the Textile Integrity Guild.
- New York City parks (2 of 3 folders), 1909-1918 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  Includes documents related to the Central Park Rehabilitation Committee, later the Parks Advisory Committee, and its maintenance efforts for New York City's public parks. Photographs of Central Park.
- New York City parks (1 of 3 folders). Oversize, 1936 (Folder Oversize-Medium)
  Blueprint of geological sign for the Great Lawn in the lower reservoir site of Central Park.
- Parks Advisory Committee (3 folders), 1912-1914 (Box 6, Folder 13-15)
  Includes correspondence and records detailing the work of the Parks Advisory Committee in the maintenance of New York City's parks.
- Park Avenue Improvement Association, 1913-1914 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Political campaigns, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  Records of contributions to the campaign of Henry H. Curran for the presidency of the borough of Manhattan including those of John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller Jr.
- Correspondence, William George Jordan, 1910-1912 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Exploration, 1908-1911 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  Correspondence and clippings regarding Robert Peary's exploration of the North Pole as well as Charles Bernheimer's own exploration activities.
- Real estate, 1910-1911 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  Includes correspondence related to personal real estate inquiries.
- State Charities Aid Association, 1910-1912 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  Includes correspondence, photographs, and pamphlets related to Charles Bernheimer's contributions to the Children's Department of the State Charities Aid Association.
- Subway system, 1906-1911 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  Includes records regarding the planning of inter-borough subway systems.
- Newspapers, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  Clippings regarding peace.
- Family ancestry, 1877-1914 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  Includes details of Charles Bernheimer's ancestry as well as notebooks in German, French, and English from Bernheimer's time in school.
- Miscellaneous, 1910-1912 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  Includes biographical clipppings and notes; political correspondence; and correspondence related to trade and labor.
- Photographs (1 of 2 folders), 1910-1926 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  Photographs of Charles L. Bernheimer and his wife Clara Silberman Bernheimer.
- Photographs (1 of 2 folders). Oversize, 1910-1926 (Folder Oversize-Medium)
  Photograph of Charles L. Bernheimer.
- Scrapbooks, 1919-1928 (Box 7)
  Two scrapbooks containing clippings related to Bernheimer's work in public service and exploration.